[PART 1]
I've got a quiz here about money.
Would you like to do it with me?
Sure, what's the first question?
Here it is.
The smallest coin in the
United States is the cent.
How much does it cost to make 1 cent?
1 cent?
Well, that's not much.
I think it probably costs something
like 0.0001 cent to make it.
Is that right?
Completely wrong.
It costs two point four cents
What?
So the value of a cent is
less than it costs to make 1.
That's right.
And it costs 5.7 cents to
make a 1 dollar banknote.
A US dollar costs twice as
much money to make as a cent.
But it's worth 100 times more.
Funny, isn't it?
Funny?
That doesn't make any sense.
OK.
Here's another one.
How much of the world's money is real?
What do you mean real?
I mean, actual coins and banknotes.
Things you can touch.
Because a lot of our
money isn't really there.
It's computer data.
We use online bank transfers
or bank cards a lot of the time.
I see.
I'd go for 50 per cent.
Something like that.
Wrong again.
Only 8 per cent of the money we
use is actually something we can touch.
The rest is just numbers on a screen.
Wait a minute.
So maybe in the future,
we will be using bank
cards more and we'll be
doing more online shopping.
That means that we
might not have real money.
Yes.
Money won't be a thing we
can touch or carry around.
It won't exist in the real world.
We will just send data from
one computer to another.
That's crazy.
So what is money then?
Good question.
Here's another one.
How many trees are cut
down to make banknotes?
Oh, probably lots.
So that's why it's good if there won't
be so much real money in the future.
No, the answer is zero.
Banknotes aren't made of paper.
They're usually made of cotton or linen.
The same stuff as your t-shirt.
And at the moment, seven countries
only use banknotes made of plastic.
And that's increasing too.
I'm not doing very well
with these questions.
Don't worry.
Neither did I.
Here's one last question.
How many banknotes have some
kind of bacteria or virus on them?
Dirty banknotes?
I imagine they can't be very clean
because so many people touch them.
Maybe 95%.
Yes.
Actually, 94% of banknotes have
some kind of bacteria on them.
Over a nine-year period,
some British banknotes will
have gone through 2,328
different pairs of hands.
And did you know that the flu virus
can stay on a banknote for up to 17 days?
That's horrible.
I'll definitely be using my
bank card from now on.
[PART 2]
Welcome back to Money Spinners.
And our next contestant is Cindy Jones.
Hello, Cindy.
Here's your first question.
Good luck.
Which country has coins
with holes in the middle?
Is it Britain, Iceland,
Japan, or South Africa?
Oh, I know this.
It's Japan.
For sure.
I was there last year.
Yes, you're right.
So you have £100, well done.
Just out of interest, which
Japanese coins have holes?
The 5 and the 50 yen coins, I think.
Absolutely right.
But you've still only got £100.
So, okay.
Here's your next question for £250.
Which day of the week is the one
when most people use a cash machine?
Is it Monday, Thursday,
Friday, or Saturday?
Well, of course I don't
know, but I'll guess.
I think it's probably Friday.
Why?
Well, it's the start of
the weekend, isn't it?
So I think that's when people
most want some money to spend.
It's a good guess, Cindy.
And it's correct.
Around the world, more
money is taken out of cash
machines on Fridays than
any other day of the week.
Okay, Cindy, you have £250
and here's your next question.
We all know that most
of the money in the world
doesn't exist as actual
coins and bank notes.
It's just numbers, figures,
and computer records.
But what percentage of all the
money in the world is coins and notes?
Is it 8%, 12%, 20% or 50%?
Hmm, it can't be as high as 50,
and I think 20% is very high too.
So 8 or 12?
Well, I'm sure it's a low
percentage, so I'll say 8%.
You say 8%, and that is absolutely right.
That puts you at £500.
Well done.
How do you feel?
Actually, I'm pretty calm now.
Great.
Okay, question 4 for £1000.
We often talk about paper money, but
many bank notes are made of plastic.
Which country was the first country
to produce plastic bank notes?
Is it Sweden, Germany, the US or Australia?
I know this.
I read it somewhere ages ago.
It's Australia.
Sure.
It's for £1000.
I'm sure.
And it's the right answer.
And it's got you £1000.
Okay, this is where it gets serious.
A wrong answer now, and
you'll leave here with nothing.
I know.
Okay, so here's your next question.
Remember, you don't have to answer it.
What's the name of the
world's first known coin?
In other words, the oldest coin
in the world that we know of.
Is it the Egyptian lira, the Lydian lion,
the Ying Yuan, or the Saxon shilling?
No idea at all.
It's probably Ying Yuan,
but no, I really don't know.
I'll take the £1000, please.
Fair enough.
Cindy Jones, you have won £1,000!
And Cindy, if you'd said Ying Yuan,
you would have lost your money.
The correct answer is B, Lydian lion.
Applause please for Cindy Jones.
[PART 3]
Money matters.
It's said that the
easiest way to be really
rich is to be born into
a really rich family.
That aside, undoubtedly, the best way
to become truly wealthy is to get a good
idea for a product, make it and sell it,
then sit back and watch the money come in.
Throughout history, many people
have become incredibly wealthy that way.
There's nothing new in this.
For centuries, people have had ideas,
made things and become very rich,
but questions are increasingly
being asked about the way we're going.
How fair is it for one person to have a
personal fortune of billions of dollars?
Is it right for big company
bosses to be paid huge
salaries and often to receive
large bonuses on top of that?
In just one year, the
head of a building company
in the UK received 75
million pounds in bonuses.
Is that acceptable?
In 1978, bosses in the UK's
biggest companies earned on
average about 30 times an
ordinary employee's salary.
In 1988, it was 47 times.
But by 2020, this had
increased to 133 times.
We'd like to hear your
comments on this subject.
A.
I left school with a guy I know, and
we went to work in a finance company.
His father’s one of the
directors, so now he's got a
very well-paid job, earning
five times as much as me.
By the time he's 30,
he'll have earned millions,
and he does everything
he can not to pay tax.
It's sickening!
GBarker95
B.
I'm not sure what the problem is.
It's just how the world is.
Like the article says,
there's nothing new here.
Some people get lucky, some don't.
Look at writers.
Lots of people get an idea
and write a book, or books, and
sometimes thousands of people
buy the book and the writer gets rich.
They're not even always the best writers.
That's just how it is.
Thatcherman
C.
One time I heard a politician
say it's fine for people
to be extremely rich, as
long as they pay their taxes.
I agree.
A top boss, after ten years
of work or so, will have given
millions of pounds back
in taxes to help the country.
And that benefits everyone, right?
Arguer123
D.
My mum's a doctor, and
she'll be working until she's 60.
35 years of work.
And when she stops, she
won't have made a tenth
of what some of these
people make in a year.
And there are people
who manage the hospitals
she works in, who earn
five times what she does.
Who contributes more to healthcare, a
doctor, or someone who works in management?
It's disgraceful.
Aliboy
[PART 4]
Money, past, present, and future.
Thousands of years
ago, people started using
metal coins as money
to buy and sell things.
But the coins were heavy,
so paper money was invented.
Different payment systems
evolved through time,
and now we also use
credit and debit cards.
These cards often have to be put into a
machine, and then a PIN has to be tapped in.
But that practice is
disappearing, with contactless
cards and smartphone apps
becoming more and more popular.
So cash has mostly been replaced
by alternative payment methods.
And things don't stop there.
It's possible that some countries
will soon be completely cashless.
For example, it's
predicted that no one in
Sweden will be using
cash at all by about 2025.
So, what is the future of money?
20 years from now, will
we still be using cash?
The answer is undeniably
no, and it's highly likely
that bank cards are
on their way out as well.
This is happening already.
The use of smartphones, smart
watches and electronic wristbands
has allowed people in many
situations to avoid using cash or cards.
Some apps let us transfer money
from phone to phone like a text message,
which makes it a quick and easy way
to repay a friend if you owe them money.
Increasingly, people are making invisible
payments for things like car rides.
You choose a car, you
take the ride, the money
automatically comes out
of your registered card.
You can even include a
tip for your driver this way.
Perhaps we will soon be doing
this in places like supermarkets too.
You'll get your goods, a reader will
record the details of what you've bought
as you leave, and and the amount will be
taken automatically from your account.
And if you need a refund,
the money is put back
in your account as
easily as it was taken out.
Worry free shopping,
no machines or long
checkout queues, no more
heavy wallets or purses.
This all sounds very positive, but
there are possible disadvantages too.
Technological advancement,
as we all know, brings many
positives, but also forces
us to consider other matters.
Will fraud, especially online, get easier?
And as our money systems become
more dependent on computers,
how can we make sure
that the computers don't fail?
Security might get better as we increase our use
of things like fingerprint and face identification,
but will they be used to invade our privacy
by gathering information about our movements?
By far, that's the most important question.
Questions like these won't go away easily.
We are in a state of change, and there
are many different future possibilities.
Perhaps unimagined payment
methods will be developed.
It will be interesting to see how things
move forward, but one thing is for sure.
In 20 years time, we
won't be buying, selling,
and paying the same
way that we do now.
[PART 5]
You will hear Connor talking about
the royal mint, where coins are made.
For questions 1-10, complete the
sentences with a word or short phrase.
I'd like to talk to you
today about the royal mint.
I should explain that I'm a numismatist,
which means my hobby is collecting coins.
That's why I'm so
interested in the royal mint.
It's where all the UK's coins are made.
The headquarters of the royal mint is in
South Wales in a town called Llantrisant.
I've never been there, but I've
seen photos and it looks amazing.
It's massive.
There's no bigger mint
on the planet, and it uses
the most amazing technology
to produce the coins.
One thing I should mention is that
not all the UK's money is made here.
The banknotes are made
by the Bank of England,
which is a different
organisation altogether.
The royal mint is also extremely old.
It was started during the
reign of King Alfred in 886.
That's more than 1,100 years ago.
At that time, there were several
mints all over the country, but
in 1279 all coins were made in
one place, the Tower of London.
The mint stayed in London until 1968
when it moved to its current site in Wales.
The new buildings were
opened by Queen Elizabeth II.
As I've already said, the
royal mint is a really big place.
It takes up 35 acres, which is
about the size of 23 football pitches.
It's also a huge employer
offering jobs to 900 people.
As you can see, it's really
important for employment in the area.
Work at the site goes on for 24 hours
a day, 7 days a week, 52 weeks a year. it literally never stops.
So it’s not surprising that it has
the potential to produce 90 million
coins a week, which means its
yearly output is around 5 billion coins.
Of course, that's more coins
than the UK needs each year.
The mint also makes coins
for other countries, around
60 countries in all get
their coins from the UK.
So far, I've only
talked about coins, but
the royal mint makes
other products as well.
One of the things it produces
is something called a blank.
A blank is a metal disc
which is the size of a
coin but doesn't have
anything printed on it.
Blanks can be made into coins
somewhere else at a later date.
The mint also produces medals and coins to celebrate special occasions.
They're always limited editions
and can become quite valuable.
These are the coins that got
me interested in the hobby.
I started in 2012, which was a good
year because the mint made special
coins to celebrate the Queen's Diamond
Jubilee and also the London Olympics.
I've got them both.
Talking of collecting, the royal mint
has an amazing collection of its own
with examples of almost all the coins
it's produced since the 16th century.
It keeps them in the
Royal Mint Museum and
you can see most of
them on its online pages.
Unfortunately, you can't visit the
museum in person to see the collection.
In fact, you can't visit the mint at all.
Until a few years ago, you could
have a guided tour around the
museum but they stopped them
because they were worried about safety.
It's a real shame because a trip to the
Royal Mint would be my dream day out.